Do you also feel that health insurance is becoming more
expensive? Do you think
its premiums have become so
unaffordable in the long term? Health
inflation is set at 14%, which means
insurance company premiums will definitely increase every year. So, there
is a beautiful tool with which you can reduce your health insurance
premium. This is called a
deductible. Let's understand what a deductible is with an
example. So basically, you can see that
this is your claim amount.
Suppose you went to the hospital and
your claim came for this amount. Now you have chosen a deductible.
What does deductible mean in a policy? You will pay this small amount
initially, and the insurance company will pay the remaining claim amount on top of that. You will pay this
small amount, and the
insurance company will pay the remaining claim amount on top of that.
What will the insurance company give you in return? A discount. So, you
can choose a deductible, and yes, you have to pay this only once a year.
Suppose the first claim comes, then
we take the initial deductible amount.  If
you have taken a deductible of Rs 25,000, then
you will pay Rs 25,000 as claim amount and the
insurance company will pay the rest. This is
only once a year. Whatever next claim comes, the
insurance company will settle it in full and you will
not have to pay it again. So this is how the
deductible works. In return, the
company gives you a discount. So today we will
also see the single calculation whether
taking a deductible is really beneficial or
not. Before starting the video, I would
like to introduce myself. My
name is Gurleen Kaur Tikku and I am a
Certified Financial Planner. I have been associated
with the insurance industry for the last 18 years
and every week I bring videos for you
so that your personal
financial life can become easy and happy
because the tagline of our company is
Creating Wealth of Happiness. Let's move on to today
's video.
We will see the comparison between deductible and no deductible. So
here, as you can see on the screen,
I have taken the premium for a family
of four. It is a family of four people, husband and
wife, 36.  I am 34 years old and have two children, four and two.
I have taken the premium for January 1, which is in
Delhi, Delhi NCR, Mumbai, Navi Mumbai,
Gujarat. The premium for this January is
less in many policies.
Here, I have taken a family floater policy where
all four are sharing the cover and have taken a
sum shot of Rs. 10 lakh. If I had paid the
premium straight forward and
not even talked about the deductible, my premium would have been
approximately Rs. 10 lakh. I have taken an approximate premium. So,
those calculations will be easy for us. The
annual premium would have been Rs. 33,000. If I say here that I
take a deductible of Rs. 25,000, that is, Rs. 25,000, then I get a discount of Rs.
25,000. This means
what will be my savings? Rs. 33,000 - Rs. 25,000 = Rs.
8,000. Now, I have taken a
second option of taking a deductible of Rs. 50,000.
This deductible will vary in different policies. The
deductible amount and
discount amount are for sum shot.  It will be decided accordingly, so
you can check in different policies. I have taken just one
example, now I have taken a higher
deductible, which means I am saying
that if I pay more money in the total claim, then
what will happen, the discount will increase.
Simple logic, I am saying that initially
I will pay more. Earlier I was
saying that I will pay 25000, so the company
said, okay, you take a 25% discount on the total
premium. Now I am saying that I will pay
more. Instead of 255000, I will pay 000.
So what will the company do, it will
increase the discount. Then I will say that
instead of 50000, I will pay 1 lakh.
You have to decide this at the time of taking the policy
or you can change it at the time of renewal. I
said I want to take a deductible of ₹1 lakh, which is
100k, then my discount will
increase further because the company knows
that I do not have to pay the first ₹1 lakh, so in this
way the discount will increase as
you increase the deductible.  You will go but it is
important for you to understand that you have to bear the deductible amount
firstly secondly I
saw here that with 50000 there is a discount of 40
it means my premium
becomes 33000 ₹2000000 saving of ₹1 thirdly
I said I get a discount of 50 on
33000 if I take a deductible of 100k
which is ₹1 lakh only once a year then
my saving is 16000 my
premium becomes 50 approximately if it falls then
17000 is my saving in a way this is an
estimate now you will say it should be 16500 16500
I have kept 16 and 17 to keep it simple it will
not make much difference
I will take this scenario below I have assumed
that you keep running the policy for 4 years and
your claim does not come then what will happen the
discount that you are getting on the premium
what is your saving so whatever you  You are
getting a discount every year and you will
save money. So I have taken an example
that you did not make a claim for 4 years, then
if you had taken a regular policy then you would have paid 33000 *
4, that means you would have paid 132000 premium.
33000 * 4. Right now I have not assumed that the
premium will increase due to inflation and
so on. I have tried to keep it simple.
If you had taken a deductible of 25000 then your
premium would have been after % discount
₹2500000. If you are
paying for 4 years then you are
paying a total premium of ₹1 lakh in 4 years.
What is your discount? 132 lakh.
You saved 32000 in 4 years. Okay, then
we discussed that if you take a deductible of 50k
then in the same way you will pay ₹2000000 annually.
You will pay 8000 in 4 years.
Your saving will be 52000. If you  If you had
paid the full premium, you would have paid Rs 132,000.
Now, if you had paid a premium with a deductible,
your savings would have been Rs 52,000. Now, if you talk about a
deductible of Rs 100,000, it
means a deductible of Rs 1 lakh. In that case,
your premium is Rs 1,16,000. You will
pay it four times. If you take a four-year scenario,
you are paying Rs 64,000. So,
how much will your savings be? Rs 132,000 - Rs 64,000. So,
you have saved approximately Rs 68,000 in four years. If your
claim does not come, then if a claim comes in year five,
what will happen in that case?
In the first scenario, your net profit of Rs 77,000
is a kind of profit, which means you saved Rs 77,000
if you had taken a deductible of Rs 255,000. In
scenario one, now let us talk about scenario
two, where you have taken a deductible of Rs 50,000.
What happened here?
How much money did you lose from your pocket in the fifth year?
How much money did you spend from your pocket? ₹5000000 Because you had
taken a deductible of 50000, so a
claim of 50000 out of 1 lakh will be settled net net. You have
taken a deductible of ₹2000000
What happened here was that a claim of ₹1 lakh came,
you paid the entire 1 lakh, the insurance company did
not pay it because your deductible
amount is only ₹1 lakh. Your profit above 68000 was
yours, so here net net you incurred a
loss of ₹4000, which means you had to pay ₹000
from your pocket because you had
chosen a deductible option of 1 lakh.
So here also if you have
corporate insurance or you have any
other insurance policy, then you
can claim this initial deductible amount from there,
so this profit loss scenario will not
remain for you, this is only when you have any other insurance policy.  There is
no insurance cover and you have to
pay the deductible amount in cash. Now let
us discuss further what happens in the long term. Let
us discuss the policy and it runs for 5 years. So the
same scenario is there, you are paying Rs. 33,000
here. You are paying Rs. 25 as deductible of Rs. 25,
and you are
paying Rs. 20,000 as deductible of Rs. 50,000 and you are paying Rs. 16,000 as
deductible of Rs. 1 lakh. So
what happened here, we took it, there was
no claim till year 9, after that you paid Rs. 25,000, then
you paid Rs. 25,000 for the next 5 years, so in year 9
you paid Rs. 225,000. In the first scenario
you paid Rs. 97,000. If you have paid the premium for 9 years, the
full premium is Rs. 33,000. Here
I am saying again that I have not considered the premium increase as per age due to
inflation.
For simple calculations,
I will pay the premium for Rs. 255,000 deductible for 9
years.  I will pay 225000 and 50000 in deductible,
180000 and 144000 in lakh deductible,
means you understand that that was
scenario one that the claim came in the fifth year,
we call this scenario one,
what happened then, let's change its color a little,
okay and this is scenario two that your
claim came here, no claim came for 10 years, so
what will happen in that case,
claim came in the 10th year and claim came in the fifth year,
so here the saving that you are doing is,
you are saving ₹ 72000 in 25000 deductible,
means the total amount you had to pay is
97000, but with deductible you paid
225000, so you saved 72000,
in the first scenario with 50000 deductible you
saved 117000, with 1 lakh deductible
you saved  Saved ₹ 53000 Now we are saying
that the claim came in year 10.
Claim did not come till the ninth year. Claim came in the 10th year.
Now what will happen? A claim of ₹ 1 lakh came.
In the first scenario, the insurance company will
pay the entire amount. What will happen in the second scenario?
You will pay ₹ 5000 and the
insurance company will pay ₹ 75000. So what will be the calculation that
if we subtract your claim
amount from the savings of ₹ 72000, that is, you had a profit of ₹ 72000 and
you paid ₹ 25000 as claim, then 72000 -
25000 is ₹ 47000. So your net saving was ₹
47000. Now this deductible
amount was more. The deductible was ₹ 50000,
so your savings were more. You had
saved ₹ 17000. Here 0000 and
You had to pay the deductible, the premium
is 1000 and you are saving 50000 for the deductible,
you are paying for the deductible, so your
savings will be ₹ 7000. In the third scenario,
how much did you save?
You paid ₹ 153000 in the claim, which came in the 10th year,
still your savings are
53000. So here you are seeing
what is happening in your claim in the long term, you are saving,
your money is being saved and what is more, the
premium will also remain under control because
with the deductible you are always going to get a discount
on the premium, whether it is 25 or
50, it will depend on the different
deductible amounts, so there is profit in the long run, so
I would
like to conclude that it depends on you, according to me, you should
take a policy with minimum deductible, which we were talking about, it is
easy to pay a small deductible amount.  If you pay the claim from your pocket tomorrow,
it is an easier amount if you pay
with a large deductible. If you are
prepared that you can pay a large deductible,
take a large amount deductible only at the time of claim. Otherwise,
with a small amount, everyone can take a policy
whether they have corporate
insurance, backup or not.
What will happen with this is that your premiums will
remain under control and at the same time you will
also get discounts. Secondly, we also
think that perhaps we may
not need to make a health insurance claim,
so this is a solution for that too. If you do
not make a claim, then clearly you are saving.
Even if you make a claim, there is no loss in the long run.
So this Excel sheet will help you
whether you should take a deductible or
not. This was my take, this is my
thinking and according to what my experience says,
I have prepared this Excel sheet for you. If you have any
questions, please
ask in the comment section. If you have any feedback, please
share it in the comment section. And
before leaving, a quick reminder, if
you have not done so far  If you have not subscribed to our channel, do
subscribe so that you get the right
information at the right time.
We will keep bringing such great videos for you.
See you in the next video. Till then,
stay safe, take care. Bye bye. Why video for you every week?
Because I forgot to say what I had to
say, no claim has come in 4 years. To
shoot this video, I have to stop it
and then it gets hot so that the
voice becomes clear. Let us talk to you people about the
policy and it has been running for four years, if I have
paid in a year then there is
something wrong with Rs. 225000.
Slowly
[Praise] a
little
bit